是, 大臣  第2季第2集
THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
压制：beiming6@TLF  字幕：破烂熊
仅供交流  严禁商用
-=破烂熊字幕组=-
翻译:四明狂客 校对&时间轴:tpring
无功受禄
办公设施方面真的不能削减开支了?
We can't economise in accommodation?
恐怕不能 大臣
'Fraid not, Minister.
信息处理设备方面呢?      不可能 到底了
Data-processing equipment? Not possible.
成人教育预算?      很不幸 没法削减
The further education budget? Sadly, it can't be.
好吧 至少本科教育开支有所减少
At least the universities won't cost us as much,
外国学生学费抵了教育开支
with overseas students paying fees covering education costs.
除非您批准例外提案...      不 很抱歉 绝无例外
Unless you make exceptions...? No, sorry, no exceptions.
至少这方面还能省
At least, that's one saving.
大臣 已经…      哦 当然
Minister, it's... Yes, of course.
恐怕就到这里了 散会
That's all, I'm afraid. Meeting over.
多谢      谢谢
Thank you Thank you.
大臣 在汉弗莱爵士来之前
Before Sir Humphrey comes,
首相府授勋秘书要您批准部门授勋名单
Number 10 asked you to approve recommendations for the honours list.
伯纳 你问了八遍了
That's the eighth time you've asked.
难道授勋就是部里的头等大事吗?
Are honours the most serious concern of this department?
是的 榜上有名的人整天守着电话 有的三天没合眼了
They are to the people on the list. Some haven't slept fordays.
急什么急? 大臣几时否决过文官受勋?
What are they worried about? Ministers never veto honours.
几乎没有 但理论上有可能 越拖他们越心慌
It's possible. They're worried about the delay.
他们怎么知道的? 文件上写着"绝密"
How do people know they're listed? Its marked "Strictly Confidential"
哦 大臣
Oh, Minister...
是我犯傻
Silly of me.
真希望他们能花四分之一的精力削减开支
If they'd put some of that effort into cutting expenditure...
怎么才能让人们对节约
How can I make people want economies
像对帝国勋章 大巴思勋章一样热心呢?
in the same way they want OBEs and KCBs?
我觉得... 不 不 不...
I've been thinking... No, no, no.
什么?      不 不 没事
What? No, no, nothing...
来吧 伯纳 说出来
Spit it out.
我没资格...我不提倡 也不支持 但是
It's not my place, and I couldn't possibly recommend it...
如果您不批准公务员授勋
Suppose you were to refuse to recommend any honours
除非他们削减预算5%如何?
for civil servants who hadn't cut their budgets by 5 %?
伯纳      对不起 大臣 我…
Bernard! Sorry, Minister...
不 伯纳 这太妙了
No, Bernard! It's brilliant!
好主意 公务员就这一个死穴 对吗?
It's the answer. It's the only hold we have over the civil servants.
我管不了他们加薪 或者晋升
I can't stop their pay rises or their promotions.
不写他们的工作报告 但我可以不给他们授勋
I don't even write their reports, but I can with hold their honours!
干得好 伯纳      是您自己想到的 大臣
Well done. You thought of it, Minister.
不 不 是你想出来的      不 是您想出来的
No, no, you thought of it. No, you thought of it.
求您
Please!
请少加点 谢谢
Just a touch, please. Thank you very much.
真是丰盛的晚餐 院长 我一向乐意叨扰府上
Splendid dinner. I always enjoy my visits here.
今后怕是来不了喽 汉弗莱
I'm afraid this could be your last.
怎么?我把酒传错方向了吗?
Why? Did I pass the port the wrong way?
告诉他吧 财务处长      贝利学院快破产了
Tell him, Bursar. The college's going to the wall.
多亏你们部的新政 对外国学生收全额学费
It's your new policy of charging overseas students full rates.
牛津大多数学院还能应付
Other Oxford colleges can cope,
但是贝利的外国学生向来是最多的
but we've always had many overseas students here at Baillie.
对 可是全额就全额 有什么关系
You simply charge them a full fee, no problem.
可他们付不起 四千磅一年? 没人肯来
Unless they can't pay ?,000 a year. They won't come.
我跑遍世界 甚至到美国筹款 兜售牛津教育理念
I've been all over the USA selling them the idea of an Oxford education
非洲满是英国教授
Africa is crawling with British professors
拼命要把社会学课程塞给当地人
frantically trying to flog sociology courses to the natives.
在印度和中东 也是你死我活
And India and the Middle East. Competition is cut-throat.
何不改招英国本国学生?
Why not fill up vacancies with British undergraduates?
一点都不好笑 汉弗莱
I don't think that's awfully funny, Humphrey.
我没说笑话      老伙计 怎么能招本国学生
I wasn't trying to be funny. Anything but home students!
为什么?      一名英国学生只能收500磅
Why? We only get 500 a head forthem.
400人才抵得上50个外国学生
We'd have to take 400 to replace a mere 50 foreigners.
师生比例会从1:10变成1:34
The staff/student ratio would go from 1:10 to 1:34.
教室和寝室会挤得像沃伍德监狱
We'd have classrooms, dormitories... like Wormwood Scrubs!
或者像苏塞克斯大学
Or the University of Sussex!
院长估计这些画能卖两三万磅
The Master thinks the pictures mayfetch ?030,000.
画加上银器
The pictures and silver together
刚够新教学楼的贷款利息
might just pay the mortgage interest.
天啊 天啊
Dear, oh, dear!
当然 也可以让政府对我们网开一面
Orwe could get the Government to treat us as an exception.
有趣的是 汉弗莱
Interestingly, Humphrey,
这个权利似乎在你的大臣手上
it seems to be your Minister who has the authority.
怎样才能说服大臣认同贝利学院的重要性呢?
Howmight one persuade aMinister of the importance of Baillie College?
我不知道 不如请他来出席贵宾晚宴?
Why not get him down to a High Table dinner?
以他的智商能理解我们的状况吗?
Is he of the intellectual calibre to understand our case?
可以吧
Oh, yes!
这么简单的状况
It's intelligible to anyone
连维尼熊都能理解
with the intellectual calibre of Winnie the Pooh!
就是
Quite!
哈克的智商能比上维尼熊?
And Hacker is of the intellectual calibre of Winnie the Pooh?
哦 可以的
Oh, yes!
状态好的话
On his day.
早安 大臣      早安 汉弗莱
Morning, Minister. Morning, Humphrey.
有两件事 大臣
Two things, Minister.
首先 部里推荐的授勋名单
Firstly, the departmental recommendations for the honours list.
又是授勋名单      是的 大臣
The honours list again! Yes, Minister.
先放一放好吧?      不能放 大臣
Let's leave that for the moment. We can't leave it, Minister.
快到5星期期限了      5星期?
It's getting nearthe five weeks. Five weeks?
对 凡授勋都要提前5星期通知
All recipients are notified five weeks before.
好让他们有时间拒绝
It gives them time to refuse.
几时有公务员拒绝过授勋?
When did a civil servant last refuse an honour?
应该是财政部那位 拒绝骑士头衔
Somebody in the Treasury refused a knigh thood.
天啊 哪年?      似乎是1496年
When? I think itwas 1496.
为什么?      他有一个了
Why? He'd already got one.
大臣 如果您已经批准...      汉弗莱
Lf you've approved the list... Humphrey...
你知不知道20%勋位都授给了公务员?
Did you know that 20 % of honours go to civil servants?
这是对他们勤奋工作的适当奖赏 大臣
Afitting tribute to their devotion to duty.
不 他们已经拿薪水了
That's what they get paid for.
我们这些人得有特殊贡献才能得荣誉
The rest of us have to do something special to get an honour.
为弱智儿童工作20年才换一枚帝国勋章
They work for years with the mentally handicapped to get an MBE.
而你们的骑士头衔水到渠成
Your knigh thoods simply come up with the rations.
大臣 女皇陛下的公务员们一辈子
Minister, her Majesty's civil servants spend their lives
领取微薄薪水 最终默默无闻地退休
working for a modest wage and at the end retire in to obscurity.
荣誉只能稍微告慰他们为国家
Honours are a small reward for a lifetime of loyal,
和女王忠贞不渝 鞠躬尽瘁的一生
self-effacing discretion and devoted service to the nation.
微薄薪水?      唉 是的
"A modest wage"? Alas, yes.
汉弗莱 你一年的薪水超过三万镑
You get over?0,000 a year!
比我还多七千英镑      对 可是相比之下仍算微薄
That's ?,000 more than I get. But still relatively modest.
跟谁比?
Relative to whom?
像伊丽莎白·泰勒
Elizabeth Taylor, for example.
汉弗莱 你和伊丽莎白·泰勒毫无可比性
You are not relative to Elizabeth Taylor.
你们俩截然不同
There are important differences.
可不是 她又没在牛津拿过第一
Indeed, yes. She didn't get a first at Oxford.
你也不会默默无闻退休
And retire into obscurity?
你拿大笔养老金 去石油公司和银行做董事
You take a massive pension and become directors of oil companies.
那也是默默无闻的董事
But very obscure directors.
还没有炒鱿鱼之忧 干工业的 犯错误你会被解雇
You're in no dangerof the sack. In industry, you get the boot.
做公务员 你犯错误 我被解雇
In the civil service, if you screw up, I get the boot!
很好笑 大臣 那份名单...      不行 汉弗莱
Very droll, Minister. The list... No, Humphrey.
我不会白批 公务员得自己挣来荣誉
I'll not approve any honour to any civil servant who hasn't earned it.
您说什么"挣来"?      挣来就是挣来
What do you mean, "earned it"? I mean "earned it".
无功不受禄      这种事闻所未闻
Done something to deserve it. But that's unheard of!
我的新政要求部里所有公务员每年
My new policy is to withhold all honours from civil servants
削减预算5% 否则不给授勋
who do not make a cut in their budgets of 5 % per year.
你是不是默许啦?
Your silence indicates approval?
绝不是 您哪来这么荒谬的想法?
It does not! Where did you get that preposterous idea?
是...
It...
我突然想到的      荒唐透顶 闻所未闻 不可能
...just came to me. It's ridiculous! Unheard of!
怎么?      这整个想法就...
The whole idea is... It's...
它从根本上危及...
It strikes at the very roots of...
它是灭亡的前兆
It's the beginning of the end!
是导火索 是左翼激进主义
The thin end of the wedge! A Bennite solution!
然后呢? 您要废除君主制吗?
What next? Abolition of the monarchy?
别发傻 汉弗莱
Don't be absurd.
这个体系一直完美运转 无需改变
The system has worked so well in the past.
它不完美
It hasn't.
我们得公平审视这一体制      就知道你会说
Give it a fairtrial. I thought you might say that...
告诉你 嘉德勋章由爱德华三世设立于1348年
The Most Noble Order of the Garter was founded in 1348 by Edward III.
审判期该结束了吧?
It's at the end of its trial period now.
大臣 一旦您借经济阻碍荣誉
Minister, if you block honours pending economies,
您可能开创一个危险的先例
you might create a dangerous precedent.
你是说这次我们做对了
If we do the right thing now,
下次也非对不可?
we'll have to do the right thing next time?
天哪汉弗莱 什么都别干才是正理么      恰恰相反
Nothing would get done at all! On the contrary.
有很多事应该做 可是      不要做第一个
Many things must be done, but... Nothing done for the first time.
不 大臣
No, Minister!
我完全支持您的意图 我会全力予以贯彻
I'm fully seized of your aims, and I'll try to put them into practice.
为此目的
To that end,
我提议设立各部联席委员会广泛调查
I recommend we set up a committee with broad terms of reference,
以便最终考虑到一切后果
so we're in a position to think through the various implications
并从长远考虑角度出发作出决定
and decide based on long-term considerations
而不是仓促采取轻率 考虑欠周的行动
rather than rush prematurely into precipitate and ill-conceived actions
从而造成无法预料的后果
which might have unforeseen repercussions.
你是说"不行"?
You mean "no"?
我是说 就目前看来 等时机成熟…
I mean, as faras one can see, in the fullness of time...
不 不 不 汉弗莱
No, no, no, Humphrey.
你了解我 雷厉风行
You know me: Action now!
雷厉风行
Action now.
神志健全的人都不想被授勋
Nobody in their right mind can want honours.
授勋引起奉承 势利 嫉妒
They encourage sycophancy, snobbery, jealousy,
这些都归公务员可不公平
and civil servants shouldn't get them all!
可是大臣...      不 汉弗莱 抱歉 我主意已定
But Minister... No, no! I'm sorry. I have decided.
还有一件呢?      还有一件?
Your other point? Other point?
你说有两件事的      是吗?
You had two. Did I?
是的 抱歉 气糊涂了
Yes, I'm sorry. The shock!
大臣 昨天我会见了牛津贝利学院的代表
Yesterday, I had representations from Baillie College, Oxford.
照外国学生学费的新规定 他们一年损失二十五万
Grants for overseas students... They'll lose millions a year.
多招英国学生不就完了
They must just take more British students.
他们当然极其乐意 大臣 但是
Nothing would please them more, but you see...
贝利学院的外国学生最多
Baillie has many foreign students,
新政会严重打击
and there could be repercussions
热带病学系和国际公法系
at the schools of tropical medicine, international law,
阿拉伯语系甚至得停办
and the Arabic department may have to close down.
对不起 我不能花纳税人的钱去教育外国人
We can't educate foreigners at the taxpayer's expense.
不单单是外国人 大臣
Not just foreigners.
如果外交部没地方给新人员培训阿拉伯文化
If the diplomatic service had nowhere to immerse its recruits,
后果不堪设想 甚至会有亲以色列的外交部
the results could be catastrophic, with a pro-Israeli Foreign Office!
石油政策会变成什么样?
What would happen to our oil policy?
那么只能换个地方培训
Its recruits must go elsewhere.
还有哪能学习阿拉伯语?
Where else would they learn Arabic?
阿拉伯?
Arabia?
事实上 大臣 贝利学院确有过人之处
Baillie College has an outstanding record.
多年来 它使英国监狱人满为患      监狱?
It's filled our jails for years. Jails?
是的 您看 字母JB代表英联邦最高荣誉
Yes. The letters "JB" are the finest honour in the Commonwealth.
"JB"?      "英国犯人"
"JB"? "Jailed by the British".
甘地(印度) 恩克鲁玛(加纳) 马卡李奥(塞浦路斯)
Gandhi, Nkrumah, Makarios,
本-古理安(以色列) 肯雅塔(肯尼亚)
Ben-Gurion, Kenyatta,
尼赫鲁(印度) 穆加贝(津巴布韦)
Nehru, Mugabe.
各国领导人 无穷无尽 很有几名我们的校友
The list of leaders is endless and contains several of ourstudents.
"我们的校友"?
"Ourstudents"?
汉弗莱 你上的哪所学院?
Humphrey... which college did you go to?
大臣 这完全是题外话
That is quite beside the point.
我就喜欢聊题外话
I like being beside the point.
说来听听 汉弗莱 你上的哪所学院?
Humourme, Humphrey. Which college did you go to?
该不会刚好是贝利学院吧?
Was it Baillie, by any strange coincidence?
恰巧...我也是贝利人
It so happens... I am a Baillie man,
但这完全是两码事
but that has nothing to do with it!
对对对 两码事嘛
No, of course not.
想什么呢 不害臊
Perish the thought. Naughty.
喂? 下院分组表决 大臣
Yes? The division, Minister.
就这么定了吧 汉弗莱 没时间了
That rathersettles it. No more time.
伯纳 我该投赞成还是反对?
Am I voting "aye" or"no"?
投反对 反对党的修正案 第二读...     管它是什么
"No". It's a... I don't want to know what it is.
我只怕走错门而已
I don't want to go through the wrong door.
阿诺德?
Arnold?
汉弗莱 请坐
Humphrey! Do sit down.
希望你不介意来一趟内阁办公室
Hope you don't mind my dragging you here.
哦 没关系      我有点担心你的大臣
No, please. I was worried about your Minister.
"将勋章跟节约挂钩"
Linking honours to economies.
哦 您听说了? 纯粹胡说八道
That? A lot of nonsense.
很好 你是说没那回事
Good. You mean it's not true?
不完全...他确实是提到了
Not exactly. That is, he did just mention it.
但是...      但是什么?
But... But what?
我找不到有效论据来反驳他
I can't find any effective arguments against it.
汉弗莱 这可是导火索      我说了
It's the thin end of the wedge. That's what I said.
是左翼激进主义      我也说了
A Bennite solution. I said that.
后果不堪设想      我都说了
Where will it end? That's what I said.
确实无法容忍 但是...
No, it's intolerable, but...
又不可违抗
irresistible.
是啊 我不是指摘你 我也不了解内情
I'm not reprimanding you, I don't know the facts well enough.
但作为秘书长 我希望你保证他不会实施
I'd like your assurance that he won't be putting it into practice.
我当然希望不会
I certainly hope he won't.
"希望"恐怕不够
I'm not sure that hopes are good enough.
试想一旦你们部门实施 很快就会在政府扩散
Lfhe applied it to your department, the contagion would spread!
每一个部门
Every department!
那么 我们可以指望你咯?      我会尽力
Presumably, we can count on you? I shall certainly try.
但这...很棘手      你当然有你的办法
But... it's rathertricky. You know what you're doing.
但这可能让大家怀疑你是否可靠
This could cause people to reflect on your soundness.
当然我本人毫不怀疑 但是...
I've no doubts about you myself, but...
谈个心总是好的      当然 谢谢 阿诺德
I thought a chatwould be useful. Absolutely. Thank you.
对了 我刚刚跟我们学院的院长通了电话
By the way, I had our college master on the phone.
他说你上周在贝利参加了晚宴      是啊
He said you dined at Baillie. Right!
我保证你的大臣会给他们特殊待遇 对吧?
I assured them your Minister would treat them as a special case.
当然 当然
Yes... Yes...
我已经安排大臣参加贵宾宴会
I've got the Minister coming to a benefactors' dinner.
很好 你果然可靠
Good. Sound man.
好了 我得去10号了 感谢你过来 汉弗莱
I must be getting over to Number 10. Thanks for dropping in.
不胜荣幸
Pleasure...
阿诺德
Arnold.
据说汉弗莱爵士昨天
Sir Humphrey saw the Cabinet Secretary
被内阁秘书狠批一番      真的?
and got the most frightful wigging.
对 骂得他狗血淋头 为您的"按节约授勋"妙计
Really tore him off a strip because of your economie-honour scheme
是你的妙计 伯纳      我们商量好的
Your scheme. We've been through all that.
对 抱歉 我的妙计
Sorry. My scheme.
汉弗莱这种高级官员也会挨训吗?
Why wig someone as high up as Humphrey?
通常是很客气的 但这次显然已经无所顾忌了
Normally, it's civilised, but this time itwas no-holds-barred.
阿诺德爵士说不是故意要指摘他
SirArnold said he wasn't actually reprimanding him.
这么惨?      是啊
Bad as that, was it? Yes.
还暗示有人怀疑他的可靠程度
He suggested some people might not think he was sound.
大打出手啊      确实
A real punch-up! Indeed.
阿诺德爵士担心什么?他能拿的都拿了吧?
What has Sir Arnold to fear? He has all the honours he could want.
他才到G      G?
He has his "G". "G"?
先拿K 然后拿G      别打谜语 伯纳
You get your "G" after your "K". You speak in riddles.
先拿CMG 然后拿KCMG 最后拿GCMG
First you get the CMG, then the KCMG and the GCMG,
三等勋爵士 二等勋爵士
the Command of the Order of St Michael and St George,
大十字勋爵士
Knight Grand Cross of St George.
在部门里 CMG代表"叫我上帝"
In the service, CMG stands for "Call Me God".
而KCMG代表"请叫我上帝"
And KCMG for "Kindly Call Me God".
GCMG怎么讲?
And GCMG?
"上帝叫我上帝"
"God Calls Me God".
阿诺德爵士担心什么?他不是都拿遍了吗?
Why should SirArnold worry? He has his full quota of honours.
没有 差得远呢
Nowhere near!
还有贵族爵位 功绩勋章 荣誉三等男爵士勋章
There's a peerage, the CH
嘉德勋章 蓟花骑士勋章...
the OM, the Knight of the Thistle...
蓟花骑士? 发给谁的?
Knight of the Thistle? Who for?
苏格兰人和驴子?      二者有区别的 大臣
Scotsmen and donkeys? There's a distinction.
你是没碰到苏格兰民族主义分子
You haven't met the Scottish Nationalists!
谁管蓟花?      有个委员会就吃它了
How do they award the Thistle? A committee sits on it.
汉弗莱真以为我会改变大学财务政策
Does Humphrey think I'll change university policy
就为一个贵宾宴会?
over High Table dinner?
我听说贝利的宴会极为丰盛 大臣
I believe Baillie College give a very good dinner, Minister.
还有多远?      几分钟 40号高速很好走
How much further? A few minutes. The M40's good.
4号高速也不错
So's the M4...
为什么有两条这么好的路直通牛津
Why did we get two really good roads to Oxford
却没有一条通南安普敦或多佛 或者别的港口?
before any to Southampton or Dover or any of the ports?
几乎全体常任秘书都出身牛津 大臣
Nearly all our Permanent Secretaries went to Oxford, Minister,
牛津各学院都有很好的晚宴
and most Oxford colleges give very good dinners.
内阁纵容他们?      当然不 他们坚决反对
The Cabinet allow that? Certainly not.
他们禁止修路让文官们去牛津赴宴
They said no motorway to take civil servants to Oxford,
除非先修路让大臣们去乡下打猎
unless there was one to take Ministers hunting in the shires.
所以50年代的1号公路通往莱斯特乡间
That's why the M1 stopped in Leicestershire!
哦 少来了
Oh, come!
那刚完工的11号高速呢?
What about the M11 just completed?
剑桥各学院就不大宴宾客吗?
Doesn't Cambridge give as good dinners?
当然有 大臣 不过交通部
Yes, of course, but it's been years
多年没有剑桥出身的常任秘书了
since Transport had a Permanent Secretary from Cambridge.
作为快破产的的学院来说 晚宴不错嘛
Fora college on the edge ofbankruptcy, not a bad dinner!
菲兹沃晚宴由一笔特定基金支付
The Fitzwalter Dinner is paid forby endowment,
来自16世纪一位慷慨的赞助人
a great 16th-century benefactor.
平常我们只吃方便面拌腐乳
Most nights we eat Mother's Pride and processed cheese.
你们得找个20世纪的赞助人
You need a 20th-century benefactor.
您正好说到点子上      怎么了?
Interesting you should say that. Why?
赞助人数量稀少 相隔久远
Benefactors are few and farbetween.
艾萨克·沃尔森只是有史以来第二个被牛津
Isaac Wolfson is the second man to have a college named after him
和剑桥拿来命名学院的人      谁是第一个?
at Oxford and Cambridge. Who's the first?
耶稣
Jesus.
耶稣?      耶稣...基督
Jesus? Jesus... Christ.
我们最尊崇的那些赞助人
Some of ourmost revered benefactors are men
都曾拯救学院免遭政府掠夺
who saved the college from the depredations of Government.
他们的名字被顶礼膜拜几个世纪
Their names are remembered and hallowed for centuries.
也算是种不朽      真的?
It's a sort of immortality. Really?
说说看 这些赞助人做过什么?
What did these benefactors do?
就说威廉·德·维尔爵士 他的纹章和大名刻在教堂里
Take Sir William de Vere, his coat of arms are there and in chapel.
他在15世纪从贝利撤走了一支军队
He diverted the baronial army away from Baillie in the 15th century.
转而驻扎到了圣乔治学院
He had the soldiers billetted at St George's College.
我不知道还有圣乔治学院呢
I didn't know there was a St George's.
没有 从那之后就没有了
There isn't. Not since that.
再说乔治·蒙克顿
Then, there's George Monkton,
蒙克顿学院就是以他命名的
whom Monkton Quad's named after.
他阻止了克伦威尔融化全校银器
He stopped Cromwell melting all the college silverdown
来抵他新模范军的粮饷
to pay for his army.
他告诉他们 剑桥大学圣三一学院的银器要好得多
He told them the silverwas better quality at Trinity, Cambridge!
今后恐怕都没有学院可凭吊了
Now, it looks like there'll be no college left to remember.
当然 除非解决外国学生的问题
Unless we can solve the problem of overseas students.
当然 人总是愿意
Well, of course, one would like to...
自得其乐的...
help oneself.
呃...帮助他人
Er... help one's friends.
帮助学院
Help the college.
这与荣誉无关      当然 有此一念天理不容
Nothing to do with the honour. Of course not! Ignoble thought.
大臣坚信政治家的天职就是帮助他人
The Minister believes it's a politician's duty to help others.
完全正确 一语中的
Absolutely. Name of the game.
这才是搞政治的原因 帮助别人
That's why we go into politics, to help others.
我是个理想主义者 不为名不为利
I'm an idealist, nothing to do with the honour.
就我所见 荣誉都是身后之事
Most of the honour comes after you're dead.
可是等你入了土 你的名字铭刻在银烛台上
Not much satisfaction from having your name on the silversconce
也没多大意义了
when you're six feet under!
顺便 院长 说点别的
Incidentally, Master, to change the subject completely...
什么时候颁发荣誉博士学位?
when do you award your honorary doctorates?
颁证仪式还得几个月 但人选要在两周之内决定
The ceremonys not fora few month butwe have to decide in two weeks
荣誉博士?      人选还没定?
Doctorate? Aren't they decided?
还有个法学名誉博士空缺
There is one Doctorate of Law still to be decided.
不知该给一位法官呢 还是政府官员
We're wondering whether it should go to a judge or in Government
法官?
Judge?
才不用给法官颁法学博士呢
You don't want to make a judge a Doctor of Law!
是政治家制定法律 实施法律
The politicians make the laws and pass the laws.
没有政治家 法官们根本没法审判
If it wasn't for politicians, the judges wouldn't be able to judge.
无法可依 懂我意思吧?
There'd be no laws to judge!
当然当然      完全理解
Yes, indeed. Quite!
他们会无事可做 失业法官排成排
They'd have nothing to do. Queues of unemployed judges...
扣着可笑的假发
in silly wigs!
法官多好过
It's all right for judges.
他们不必讨好电视制片人 对记者撒谎
They don't have to suck up to TV producers, lie to journalists.
也不用假装喜欢内阁那些同僚
They don't have to pretend to like their Cabinet colleagues.
不然呢...我跟你们说...
I'll tell you something else...
要是法官得忍受我那些内阁同僚
if judges had to put up with some of my colleagues,
他们明天就会恢复死刑
they'd bring capital punishment back tomorrow!
恢复了正好
Bloody good job, too!
还有件事我得说
I'll tell you anotherthing...
我没法把他关进大牢
I can't send him to prison.
没法把他关进大牢
Can't send him to prison.
我要是法官 先把小汉关起来再说
If I were a judge, I could whiz old Humpy off to the Scrubs.
脚不落地 拖着就走 手铐咣的一声 三年后见
Feetwouldn't touch. Clang bang! See you in three years.
若诚心悔过 减刑三分之一
One third remission forgood conduct.
我整不了他
I can't do that!
还非得听他的话
I have to listen to him.
哦 老天
Oh, God!
他就念叨念叨念叨念叨
On and on and on!
有些句子比杰弗里大法官还要长
Some of his sentences are longer than Judge Jeffreys'!
不不不 政治家更该受奖赏
No, no, no. Politicians are much more deserving.
你们可不能给法官荣誉学位
You don't want to give your doctory honourates to judges.
千万不能
Definitely not!
至理名言啊 大臣
Beautifully argued, Minister.
我想通了 是不应该给法官
I see now... we shouldn't give it to a judge.
您方才讲得无比专业      简直如同法学博士 大臣
You put the case most expertly. Almost like a Doctor of Law.
我此时仿佛看到 您站在谢尔登礼堂里
I can see you there now in the Sheldonian,
绯红长袍加身 风华绝代
standing there in those magnificent crimson robes,
在诸位学术英杰面前接受博士学位
receiving doctorate in front of an assembly of eminent scholars.
太好了      棒极了
Wonderful. Marvellous.
你会说到这个 真有意思
How funny you should say that.
我刚巧也想着同样的场面呢
I was just thinking the same thing.
早安 大臣 早安 伯纳
Morning, Minister. Morning, Bernard.
昨天的晚宴真愉快 大臣
Most enjoyable dinner last night.
会议之前我想和您私下聊几句 抱歉 伯纳
I wonder if we could have a private chat. Forgive us, Bernard.
大臣
Minister...
贝利学院的院长让我问您
The master of Baillie has asked me to enquire
您是否有兴趣接受牛津荣誉法学博士学位
whether you'd accept an honorary doctorate of law.
我? 天哪
Me? Good heavens!
当然 这并不是收买您      当然不是
It's... not an offer. No, of course not.
自然 众所周知 您反感勋位
Of course, in view of your well-known hostility to honours...
别犯傻 汉弗莱 这是两码事
Don't be silly. This is quite different.
不完全是 大臣
Not entirely, Minister.
要知道 您这可是无功受禄 不是"挣来"的
It's a matter of accepting it without doing anything to deserve it,
正如您自己会直言不讳的那样
as you might put it in your refreshingly blunt fashion.
我是内阁大臣
I'm a Cabinet Minister!
您不是领薪水了吗?      对 可...不是
Isn't that what you're paid for? Yes, but... No!
对 可是...
Yes, but...
那是政府秘密投票 我又没法拒绝      当然当然
I cant refuse avote of confidence in the Government, not just oneself.
没错 但我说过 事还没定 这个...
No, quite. As I say, it's not certain, it's...
汉弗莱 还有件事      什么 大臣?
Humphrey, to change the subject completely,
我愿尽力帮助贝利学院 解决外国学生问题
Id like to do what I can for Baillie in overseas students business
哦 太好了
Oh, good!
但我的借口...理由呢?
Butwouldn't I need a pretext... a reason?
不必 大臣 没有问题
No, Minister, no problem.
据我所知 皇室正受到某些非洲领导人的压力
The Palace has been under pressure from certain African leaders.
自然不能让皇室为难
We can't embarrass the Palace,
因此可以重新指定贝利学院为英联邦教育中心
so we'll redesignate Baillie as a Commonwealth Education Centre.
可经费从哪来? 我要求各方面都削减5%预算
But where am I to find the money? Im set on 5% cuts across the board
如果这里开口 那就刹不住了
If that's achieved, anything's possible.
大臣 经费调查委员会来了      好的伯纳 带他们进来
The committee are waiting. Very well, show them in.
大臣 照我说 本部门还是能节约的
I suppose we could achieve the cuts in this department,
只要不把它联系到勋章就行了
if the absurd idea of linking honours to cuts were to be shelved.
我明白了      好的
I see. Yes...
谢谢 伯纳      早安
Thank you, Bernard. Morning.
首先回顾上次会议内容      好的
Now, minutes of the previous meeting?
好 上次议程包括 办公设施
Matters arising: Accommodation.
哦 对了
Oh, yes!
很高兴告诉大家 我们能削减5%经费
I'm happy to be able to tell you that we have found a 5 % cut,
只要出售海威库姆那幢老办公楼
by selling an office in High Wycombe.
哦 真的?      没错
Oh, really? Yes.
不错 太好了      是啊
Yes, very good. Yes.
文具购置呢?
Stationery acquisition?
是的 我们有种新的盘货制度 能减少年度支出
We've discovered a new stock control system to reduce expenditure.
减多少?      大约5% 对吗?
By howmuch? About 5 %, wasn't it?
太好了 园林管理方面呢?
Excellent! Parks and Forestry?
只要推迟购置新计算机 就能省下一笔
If we delay the new computers, we can make a saving.
是吗?能省多少?      是啊 多少?
By howmuch? Yes...?
大约5%      对 大约5%
About 5 %. Yes, about 5 %.
真的?      信息处理也能这样省
Really? That cuts data processing, too.
省多少?      能省...
By? By...
大约5%
By about 5 %.
是吗 汉弗莱 太令人满意了      是啊 大臣
This is most satisfying. Yes.
顺便 大臣 我想起一件事
Incidentally, while I think of it,
部里的受勋名单您批了吗?
have you finished with the list for the honours secretary?
批了 汉弗莱 那个没问题
Yes, Humphrey. No problem there.
伯纳会把名单给你的 伯纳?
Bernard will give it to you.
谢谢 伯纳      没事了 汉弗莱?
Thank you, Bernard. All right, Humphrey?
是 博士...呃...大臣
Yes, Doctor... er, Minister.